A Guide to the Lowell L. Koontz papers, 1951-2014
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Lowell L. Koontz papers, 1951-2014
The Library of Virginia
51326
24 cubic feet (24 boxes)
Koontz, Lowell L.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
COLLECTION IS LOCATED AT THE STATE RECORDS CENTER. CONTACT ARCHIVES RESEARCH SERVICES FOR ACCESS INFORMATION, DIRECTIONS, AND HOURS.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lowell L. Koontz, Glen Allen, 2 June 2014.
Biographical Information
Lowell L. Koontz, a native of Rockingham County, Virginia, taught science in the Fairfax (Va.) County Public Schools for 31 years, retiring from teaching in 1999. Koontz began keeping weather observations in 1956 as a school boy in Rockingham County. He built his first weather station with his father in 1958, and reported daily to WSVA Radio and to the Daily News-Record newspaper (both in the Harrisonburg area). After graduating from Virginia Tech with a Masters in Education, he took a job teaching Earth Science at Hayfield Secondary School in Fairfax County, and set up his second weather station there. A third station was established in the Bren Mar development of Fairfax County in 1979; it was moved to the Barcroft Hills area in 1986. This location was known as the Annandale station, and provided data for a weather information website started by Koontz in 1998. The site included weather observations, graphs, and weather news; severe weather warnings and discussion of forecasts for Northern Virginia; and local area records for temperature, rain, and snow. Koontz moved to Glen Allen, Virginia, in 2008 and established a new station there. He also started a new website (www.glenallenweather.com) which offered the same general types of information that the previous one had (but from the Glen Allen station), along with historical weather records gathered by Koontz for the Richmond area from various sources. As of June 2014, the station and the site are still in operation.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1951-2014, of Lowell L. Koontz, relating to his extensive collection of weather data, primarily in Rockingham County, Annandale, and Glen Allen, Virginia. Much of the material consists of information gathered from weather stations built by Koontz in these locations, and includes barograph charts, thermograph charts, hygrothermograph charts, wind charts, Nimbus records, digital photographs, and observations including temperature and precipitation totals. Also includes copies of historical Richmond-area weather records going back to 1819, obtained by Koontz from entities such as N.A.R.A., the U.S.D.A., the Smithsonian, and the U.S. Signal Service; and all files from Koontz's glenallenweather.com website through 20 May 2014.
Arrangement
This collection has been minimally processed, and for the most part remains in the order and housing in which it was received from the donor. The container listing is based on the one provided by the donor.
Contents List
- Lowell L. Koontz Papers, 1951-2014., Extent: 24 cubic feet (24 boxes).
  Papers, 1951-2014, of Lowell L. Koontz, relating to his extensive collection of weather data, primarily in Rockingham County, Annandale, and Glen Allen, Virginia. Much of the material consists of information gathered from weather stations built by Koontz in these locations, and includes barograph charts, thermograph charts, hygrothermograph charts, wind charts, Nimbus records, digital photographs, and observations including temperature and precipitation totals. Also includes copies of historical Richmond-area weather records going back to 1819, obtained by Koontz from entities such as N.A.R.A., the U.S.D.A., the Smithsonian, and the U.S. Signal Service; and all files from Koontz's glenallenweather.com website through 20 May 2014. Personal recollections and an explanation of equipment and observation procedures, compiled by Lowell Koontz in 2014, are located in Box 24.
  This collection has been minimally processed, and for the most part remains in the order and housing in which it was received from the donor. This container listing is based on the one provided by the donor.
  - 1951-1979. (Box 1)
    1. Virginia climate data, September 1957-August 1959
    2. Complete Virginia climate data, 1965-1969
    3. Barograph charts in a separate collection, 1959-1981
    4. Metropolitan climatological summaries
    5. Newspapers clippings by year, 1956-October 1979
    6. Washington Post maps, February 1975-December 1979
    7. Published National Weather Service (NWS) records, 1969-1975
    Also includes Weatherwise publications, 1950, 1952, 1957-1962, 1964-1969 (intermittent); Climate summary for all Virginia weather stations, 1951-1960; and original Naked Creek weather records, July 1960-June 1964.
  - 1980-1981. (Box 2)
    1. Original monthly records for Bren Mar Weather Station
    2. Washington Post maps, March 1980-December 1981
    3. Barograph charts in a separate collection, 1959-1981; barometer charts, 1959-1981 taken at Naked Creek Station; two barographs taking observations, 1979-1981.
    4. Hygrothermograph charts in a separate collection, 1980
    5. Metro Climate Review, 1980-1981
    6. Washington Post newspaper clippings, 1980-1981
    7. National Weather Service (NWS) maps with wind tape attached and barograph and hygrothermograph charts from October 1981 to December 1981
  - 1982-1983. (Box 3)
    2. Virginia Climate Advisory
    3. Wind charts attached to Washington Post maps January 1982-December 1983
    4. Barograph charts
    5. Thermograph charts start April 1982
    6. Hygrothermograph charts
    7. Metro Climate Review
    8. Washington Post newspaper clippings
    9. Forecast Program
    10. Printed maps with map features drawn in
    11. Storm data publications January 1982-December 1983
    12. Some Daily News Record maps
    13. Seasonal Virginia Climate Advisory
  - 1984-1985. (Box 4)
    2. Washington Post maps
    3. Wind charts attached to weather maps
    5. Thermograph charts
    11. Storm data publications ended in March 1985
  - 1986-1988. (Box 5)
    Note: There are some gaps in coverage, caused by Koontz's move to Falls Church, Virginia.
    1. Original monthly records
    3. Wind chart
    4. Barograph chart
    10. Virginia Climate Advisory
    11. Central Virginia Chapter of the American Meteorological Society
  - 1988-1989. (Box 6)
    1. Original monthly reports
  - 1990-1991. (Box 7)
    11. Presto publication
  - 1992-1993. (Box 8)
    10. National Weather Service (NWS) printed daily maps
    11. Printed maps with map features drawn in
  - 1994-1995. (Box 9)
    11. ACON publication (beginning January 1995)
    12. Printed maps with map features drawn in
  - 1995-1996. (Box 10)
    11. ACON publication
    13. Datalink publication (July-October 1995 only)
  - 1997-1998. (Box 11)
    8. Presto publication (only January-July 1997)
    9. Washington Post newspaper clippings
    10. Forecast Program
    11. Hand-drawn maps
    12. ACON publication
  - 1998-1999. (Box 12)
  - 2000-2001. (Box 13)
    9. National Weather Service (NWS) printed daily maps
  - 2002. (Box 14)
    10. ACON publication
  - 2004-2005. (Box 15)
    3. Wind charts
    5. Microbarograph charts, July 2004
    6. Thermograph charts
    7. Hygrothermograph charts
    8. Metro Climate Review
  - 2006-2007. (Box 16)
    5. Microbarograph charts
  - January-May 2008. (Box 17)
    Note: Annandale records end on 31 May 2008.
    5. Microbarograph charsts
  - Additional records, 1959-1981. (Box 18)
    Barograph charts, 1959-1981
  - Additional records, 1978-1999. (Box 19)
    Binder -- Bren Mar weather records, 1979-1986
    Binder -- Bren Mar weather records, 1978-1985
    Binder -- Annandale weather records, 1986-1992
    Binder -- Annandale weather records, 1993-1999
  - Additional records, 1979-2008. (Box 20)
    Binder -- Annandale weather records, 2000-2004
    Binder -- Annandale weather records, 2005-2008
    Binder -- Yearly summary book, 1979-2005
    Binder -- Extremes and averages, 1979-2003
  - Additional records, 1819-1897, 1997-1998. (Box 21)
    Copies of miscellaneous historical weather records, 1819-1897, from N.A.R.A. (Climatological Records of the Weather Bureau, RG-27), U.S.D.A., Smithsonian, U.S. Signal Service, etc.
    Binder -- Weather by the hour, 1997
    Binder -- Weather by the hour, 1998
  - Additional records, 1999-2008. (Box 22)
    Binder -- Weather by the Hour, 1999
    Binder -- Nimbus weather records, 2001-2002
    Binder -- Nimbus weather records, 2003-2004
    Binder -- Nimbus weather records, 2005-2006
    Binder -- Nimbus weather records, 2007-2008
  - Additional records, undated. (Box 23)
    Early feature study
  - Additional records, 1956-2014. (Box 24)
    Personal recollections and an explanation of equipment and observation procedures, compiled by Lowell Koontz in 2014
    Binder -- Naked Creek (Rockingham County, Va.) weather records, 1956-1979
    Binder -- Newspaper articles and Naked Creek (Rockingham County, Va.) weather records, 1977-2000
    CDs and DVD-Rs containing sky and ground camera images for Annandale, 2006-2008, and Glen Allen, 2008-2013, as well as movies and snow camera images for Glen Allen
    DVD-Rs containing files for glenallenweather.com website, through May 2014
    Photographs -- Naked Creek Weather Station; Annandale Weather Center; and images, 7 March 1962, of a significant snowfall in Rockingham County, Virginia
    Your Guide to the Constellations, a teacher's handbook written for Fairfax County Public Schools by Lowell L. Koontz, 1992